A Guide to the Theodore H. Berlin papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA008
Rockefeller Archive Center
Theodore H. Berlin papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1944-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Kubie, Lawrence S. (Lawrence Schlesinger), 1896-1973
Berlin, Theodore H.
Goudsmit, Samuel Abraham, 1902-
Fajans, Kasimir, 1887-
Uhlenbeck, George Eugène, 1900-1988
Yang, Chen Ning, 1922-
Brookhaven National Laboratory
Johns Hopkins University
FA008
2.5 Cubic Feet 6 document cases, 1 bound volume
Conditions Governing Access
Colllection is open for scholarly research.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 450 B456
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Theodore H. Berlin were deposited with the Rockefeller University Archives on July 1980 by Mrs. Patricia Berlin.
Related Materials
At his death a good deal of his correspondence and some notes were sent by Dr. Uhlenbeck (at the wish of Mrs. Berlin) to Kasimir Fajans to be handled with the Fajans papers in the Michigan Historical Collection, Rackham Building, Ann Arbor, Michigan. A smaller group was sent to H. A. Gersch, Georgia Institute of Technology (see Box 1, Folder 2).
Biographical / Historical
Theodore H. Berlin (1917-1962), a theoretical physicist who came to The Rockefeller University in 1962 and died suddenly in 1962. He joined the Rockefeller University Faculty with Mark Kac and George Uhlenbeck to develop a department of theoretical physics. In the short time that Dr. Berlin was at the University he so endeared himself to his colleagues that a Memorial Garden on campus was developed in his memory.
During World War II, while still a graduate student, Dr. Berlin worked on the development of the proximity fuse. His academic work was concerned with the electronic structure of molecules, and his thesis was on the quantization and electric interaction in diatonic molecules. Finally his work turned toward theoretical physics.
Married Patricia May Cleary, 1944 Children: Geoffrey N., Dennis A., Michael K., Alexander L.
Member of: American Physical Society (Fellow) Sigma Xi Phi Beta Kappa
Editor: Journal of Chemical Physics Physical Review Physical Review Letters
Chronology
1917 Born May 8, New York City
1939 B.S. Chemical Engineering, Cooper Union Institute of Technology
1940 M.S., University of Michigan
1944 Ph.D., University of Michigan (Horace H. Rackham Fellow)
1944-1946 Research physicist, University of Michigan
1946-1947 Lecturer, Johns Hopkins University
1948-1949 Associate Professor, Northwestern University
1949-1954 Associate Professor, Johns Hopkins University
1952-1953 Guggenheim Fellow, Institute of Advanced Science
1955-1961 Professor, Johns Hopkins University
1961-1962 Professor, The Rockefeller University
1962 Appointed to Board of Editors of The Physics of Fluids, starting January 1st Died November 16 and buried in Prospect Hill Cemetery, Baltimore, Maryland
Scope and Contents
Biographical material, correspondence, manuscripts, notes and notebooks, reprints, and photographs. Includes administrative correspondence with Brookhaven National Laboratory (1949-1962) and Johns Hopkins University (1952-1962). Correspondents include Kasimir Fajans, Sam Goudsmit, Mark Kac, S. Katsura, Lawrence Kubie, G. Uhlenbeck, and C. N. Yang.
Rockefeller University; Kubie, Lawrence S. (Lawrence Schlesinger), 1896-1973; Berlin, Theodore H.; Goudsmit, Samuel Abraham, 1902-; Fajans, Kasimir, 1887-; Uhlenbeck, George Eugène, 1900-1988; Yang, Chen Ning, 1922-; Brookhaven National Laboratory; Johns Hopkins University
- Biographical material (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Who's Who photocopy
  - Photographs
    - Portrait
    - Photograph with C.N. Yang
    - Memorial Garden
  - Employment record
  - Pre-employment correspondence
    - Detlev Bronk
    - Copy of letter to Sam Goudsmit
    - Copy of letter from Mark Kac to Sam Goudsmit
  - Administrative correspondence
  - Correspondence re: arrangements after death
  - Obituary Rockefeller Institute Quarterly
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence about T. Berlin papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Between G. Uhlenbeck, K. Fajans, M. Kac and H.A. Gersch.
  - A-C, 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Albrecht, M.C.
    - American Physical Society
    - Anderson, Richard L.
    - Andriola, J.
    - Bauer, Norman
    - Beardon, Alan J.
    - Breit, Gregory
    - Burdell, E.S.
    - Burlew, John S.
    - Cohen, E.G.D.
    - Cohen, Leslie
    - Cole, F.T.
    - Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, E.S. Burdell President
    - Coulson, C.A.
      1948-1949 Discussion of assumptions in the Berlin thesis.
    - Cryder Sales
  - 1949-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Brookhaven National Laboratory; ca. 1 in administrative correspondence; serving as consultant.
  - D-F, 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dieke, G.
    - Dresden, Max
    - Erpenbeck, J.J.
    - Falkoff, D.
    - Feldman
    - Fierz, M.
    - Ford, George W.
      Counter examples Kahn-Uhlenbeck theory
    - Ford, Joseph
      Discussion of work.
  - 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fajans, Kasimir
  - 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1951-1962; bulk
      Mainly while a Guggenheim Fellow
  - G-K, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gelinas, R.W.
    - Gersch, H.
    - Gildart, Lee
    - Goddard, D.R.
    - Golovin, N.E.
    - Gordon, Lewis
    - Gordon Research Conference
    - Goudsmit, Sam
    - Gourary, B.S.
    - Greenberg, Mayo
    - Groot, Siep de
    - Gursey, Fega
    - Hamilton, G.
    - Hearon, J.Z.
    - Herman, R.
    - Holmen, R.E.
    - International Congress of Theoretical Physics
    - Ising, E.
    - Ingraham, R.L.
    - Jehle, H.
    - Journal of the Optical Society
    - Kirkwood, J.G.
  - 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Johns Hopkins University Administration
      Recommendations and evaluations
      Arrangement
      Arranged alphabetically
  - 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Johns Hopkins University
      Biographical / Historical
      Acting Chairman of the Physics Department.
  - 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Johns Hopkins University
      Prepared replies for University President to H.C. Dudley on his re-examination of the theory of relativity
  - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Joost, Res
      2 manuscripts with cover letters.
  - 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kac, Mark
      With discussions of formulae. Includes unidentified snapshot.
  - 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Katsura, S.
      Includes discussions of problems; manuscript; curriculum vita; publications; 2 reprints.
  - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Kubie, Lawrence
      On theories of education for creative productivity.
  - L-O, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lax, Mel
    - Lenard, A.
    - Lidiard, Alan
    - Lipps, F.W.
    - Macek, Andrej
    - McGlinn, W.D.
    - McIlvaine, W.D.
    - Madansky, Leon
    - Markshak, R.E.
      Includes article on Soviet trip.
    - Mathematical Reviews
    - Mathot, V.
    - Mayer, Joseph E.
    - Menzel, D.E.
    - Mercier, Andre
    - Meselson, M.
    - Miller, Park H.
    - Minkowski, J.M.
    - Moe, Henry Allen
    - Mohling, F.
    - Moroi, David S.
    - Mountain, R.D.
    - Muntner, J.M.
    - Nall, J.
    - Owens, Lloyd
  - P-R, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Painter, Sidney (Mrs.)
    - Park, David
    - Plano, Richard
    - Rasetti, Franco
    - Rittner, E.S.
    - Robertson, Harry S.
    - Rodberg, Leonard
    - Rosenblatt, Samuel
  - S, 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Saperstein, M.R.
    - Scientists' Committee for Radiation Information
    - Shapiro, Anatole
    - Shipley, E.
    - Siegerst, Arnold
    - Singswald, M.
    - Sternberg, S.
    - Stein, Clara
  - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics
  - T-V, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Thomas, C.
    - Thomsen, John S.
    - Tolhoek, H.
    - Uhlenbeck, G.
    - Van Hove, L.
  - 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - United States Department of the Navy
      Primarily with Elliott Montroll on grant proposal.
  - W, 1948-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Wannier, G.H.
    - Ward, J.
    - Warner, Douglas
    - Weiss, G.
    - Weng....?, Harold
    - Wette, F.W. de
    - Weland, G.W.
    - Witten, Louis
    - Woodburne, L.S.
  - 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Yang, C.N.
  - 1953, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Zernow, L.
      Including dissertation
    - Zwansig, Robert
- Reprints and tyoescripts of publications and lectures (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Notebooks, 9 bound notebooks, some have labels, none are dated. 1 looseleaf binder. (Box 3)
  Various problems and theories. Looseleaf binder contains notes on literature.
- Assorted Notes (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  Groups of notes, undated, unnamed. Folder 1 has labeled notebook: Light and matter; theory of elementary particles. Folder 2 has labeled notebook: Magnetohydrodynamic waves.
  Pages are consecutively numbered as problems and theories worked out and so arranged.
- Assorted Notes (Box 5)
  Groups of notes.
  Pages are consecutively numbered. Notes are held together by a title of a problem or theory.
  - Assorted lecture notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes on the theory of graphs (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes on statistical mechanics (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notes on quantum mechanics (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notes on crystallography (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes on the Raleigh problem (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Feynman's Lagrangian method (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Fokker Planck equation (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Notes on statistical physics (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Notes on field theory (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Notes on low temperature (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Kac's "Random walk in the presence of absorbing barriers" (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notes on green function treatment of Schrodiner equation (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Notes on the Schwinger Hamiltonian (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Notes on free particle absorbing wall (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Notes on Quantum electrodynamics Pt. I (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Quantum electrodynamics Pt. II (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Dissertation, 1944 (Package 1)
  In fulfillment of Ph.D. requirements at the University of Michigan.